Guide to the Dan De Quille Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dan De Quille papers
1860-1956
1885-1898
WA MSS S-2667
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1
(4 boxes)
This collection consists chiefly of papers created and collected by Dan De Quille that document a portion of his writing career, circa 1860-1898, as well as a small quantity of material accumulated by his family from 1936 to circa 1956. The papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, and ephemera, as well as newspaper clippings collected by De Quille on a variety of subjects.
De Quille, Dan, 1829-1898
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the William Reese Company on William Robertson Coe Fund No. 3, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Dan De Quille (1829-1898)
William Wright (1829-1898), better known by the pen name Dan De Quille, was an American author, journalist, and humorist. He was born in Knox County, Ohio, the oldest of nine children. In 1849, he moved west with his family to West Liberty, Iowa, where he married Caroline Coleman (1829-1912) in 1853. They had five children, two of whom died in infancy. Their surviving children wereMell Wright Evans (1855-1906), Lura "Lou" Gertrude Wright (1856-1928), and Paxson George Wright (1858-1929).
In 1857, Wright traveled alone to California and prospected for gold in the foothills of the Sierra Nevada Mountains and in the Mono Lake region. In 1859, he moved to the silver mining town of Virginia City, Nevada, which extracted its mineral wealth from the Comstock Lode, the first major discovery of silver ore in the United States. In 1862, Wright began writing for the Daily Territorial Enterprise newspaper in Virginia City and adopted the pen name Dan De Quille. He remained on the staff of the newspaper for over thirty years and wrote extensively about the people, events, and mining operations in the region. From August 1863 to May 1864, he supervised the work of Samuel Langhorne Clemens (1835-1910), who adopted the pen name Mark Twain while writing for the newspaper.
In 1874, a group of mine operators in Virginia City approached De Quille to write a history of the Comstock Lode. Working in Hartford, Connecticut, under the editorship of Mark Twain, he wrote A History of the Big Bonanza (American Publishing Company, 1876).
Near the end of his life, De Quille returned to West Liberty, Iowa.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists chiefly of papers created and collected by Dan De Quille that document a portion of his writing career, circa 1860-1898, as well as a small quantity of material accumulated by his family from 1936 to circa 1956. The papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, and ephemera, as well as newspaper clippings collected by De Quille on a variety of subjects.
The correspondence in the collection encompasses letters from editors and publishers to De Quille about his writing, as well as a small quantity of letters written by De Quille to his daughter Mell Wright Evans and sister Louisa G. Wright Stevens. There is also a small group of correspondence about De Quille between his granddaughter Irma Evans Morris and Nevada historian Effie Mona Mack in 1936.
Writings by De Quille include a notebook with outlines, drafts, and notes for stories and articles. Other writings include draft manuscripts for articles about Virginia City and California, as well as about Peru, and tales based in the Middle East.
Photographs in the collection include portraits of De Quille and views of his gravesite. Ephemera in the collection includes scrapbook sheets with illustrations that De Quille clipped from magazines and newspapers to present to his granddaughter.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, circa 1860-1953. II. Writings, 1876-circa 1956. III. Photographs, circa 1885-circa 1930. IV. Other Papers, 1875-1898.
Authors, American -- 1885-1898 -- Archives; Frontier and pioneer life -- California; Frontier and pioneer life -- Nevada; Frontier and pioneer life -- Sierra Nevada Region (Calif. and Nev.); Journalists; Mines and mineral resources -- Nevada; Newspaper editors; Silver mines and mining -- Nevada; California -- Description and travel; Comstock Lode (Nev.); Nevada; Peru; Sierra Nevada (Calif. and Nev.); Virginia City (Nev.); West (U.S.) -- Social life and customs; Photographic prints; Scrapbooks; De Quille, Dan, 1829-1898; De Quille, Dan, 1829-1898 -- Pictorial works; Evans, Mell Wright, 1855-1906; Mack, Effie Mona; Morris, Irma Evans; Stevens, Louisa G. Wright, b. 1843
- Correspondence, 1863-1953; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into three subseries: Correspondence from De Quille, Correspondence to De Quille, and Third-Party Correspondence.
  - Outgoing
    Arranged alphabetically by the recepient.
    - Authors' Alliance, 1892 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Evans, Mell Wright, 1888 November 26-1893 January 24, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-11)
      Biographical/Historical note
      Mell Wright Evans (1855-1906) was a daughter of De Quille. She was married to Frank Algerman Evans (born 1852).
    - Stevens, Louisa G. Wright, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Louisa G. Wright Stevens (born 1843) was a younger sister of De Quille. She was married to Frank W. Stevens.
  - Incoming
    Arranged alphabetically by the author.
    - American Press Association, 1891 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Applegate, Josiah H., 1863 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bacheller & Johnson Newspaper Syndicate, 1891 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Barnes, E. D., 1875 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes clippings from the San Francisco Chronicle related to mining engineer Philip Deidesheimer (1832-1916).
    - Browne, J. Ross, 1875 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Letter of introduction for De Quille to Harper & Brothers publishers.
    - California Illustrated Magazine, 1893 August 23-November 24 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Clare, Ada, circa 1860-1866 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Clark, Hiram C., 1862 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Cosmopolitan Magazine, 1895 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Crawford, James, 1875 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Cummings, Amos Jay, 1891 April 6-October 22 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - D. Appleton & Company, 1895 August 2 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Daggett, Rollin Mallory, 1875 September 9 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Unsigned letter, based on its contents, it is possibly by Rollin Mallory Daggett (1831-1901), editor-in-chief of the Territorial Enterprise newspaper in Virginia City, Nevada, 1873-1878.
    - Driscoll, Dennis, 1863 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Engineering and Mining Journal, 1891 September 14-1897 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Fair, James Graham, 1885 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Goodman, Joseph T., 1863 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Hardy, Arthur Sherburne, circa 1893-1895 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Hodgson, Richard, 1893 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Lawrence, Joseph E., 1863 September 23-circa 1865 (Box 1, Folder 32-34)
    - Lester, Lirle?, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Lorborn Publishing Company, 1887 December 5-1888 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Marshall, G. M., 1864 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - McClure, Samuel Sidney, 1891 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Mining and Scientific Press, 1895 December 30-1896 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - New York Herald, 1895 May 18-1896 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Once a Week, 1892 December 27-1893 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Preston, Laura, 1865 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Rocky Mountain News, 1895 December 25 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Romance Publishing Company, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - San Francisco Call, 1895 June 11-1896 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Scribner, Elizabeth Emmeline Brewster, 1875 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Elizabeth Emmeline Brewster Scribner (born 1837) was the wife of Eben Scribner (circa 1840-1894), a mining amalgamator in Dayton, Nevada.
    - Sharon, William, 1875 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Sunday Mercury, 1874 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Taylor, Howard P., 1863 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Union Hall Hotel, Hartford, Connecticut, 1875 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Utah Press Association, 1895 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Wagoner, Hank, 1875 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Wilcox, George E., 1895 November 4 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Worthington, Alfred D., 1893 November 18-December 1 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Third-Party Correspondence
    Arranged alphabetically by name.
    - Mack, Effie Mona, to Morris, Irma Evans, 1936 May 10-October 6 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Morris, Irma Evans, to Mack, Effie Mona, 1936 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Tilton, Cecil G., to Morris, Irma Evans, 1953 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Writings, 1876-circa 1956; Series II; 18
  Writings by De Quille and others.
  Series II is organized into three subseries: Notebook, Drafts, and Writings by Others.
  - Notebook, 1880 December 26-circa 1890 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    Comprised chiefly of aphorisms and ideas for articles and stories. Includes an autograph copy of a letter by Mark Twain in the hand of De Quille about telepathy, March 29, 1875, as well as a story, "An Alaskan Legend."
  - Drafts
    Arranged alphabetically by title followed by notes and a drawing.
    - "Arabian Nights Story," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "The Blizaard," autograph manuscript poem, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - "Golden Back-Bone of the World," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - "Golden Back-Bone of the World," untitled autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - "Little Biggs and Old Bedrock," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - "Mineral Verve," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - "Nevada's Great Placer Field," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "The Nizam of Zim-Zim," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - "Peru," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - "The Washoe Club," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Untitled autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
      Discussion of animal husbandry in the Washoe Valley, Nevada, including cattle and raising geese to produce foie gras.
    - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
      Brief notes on a variety of subjects, including mining in California, contents of a proposed book, and translation of a French phrase.
    - Pencil sketch of a dog, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Writings by Others
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Lawrence, Joseph E., Untitled poem, 1876 February 8 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Unidentified, "Memories of Washoe, Nevada, 1853-1859", circa 1895 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Unidentified, Transcription of quotes about De Quille, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      Quotes by Charles Corwin Goodwin, Joseph Goodman, and Wells Drury
    - Unidentified, Transcription of an excerpt about De Quille from Irving Stone, Men to Match My Mountains: The Opening of the Far West 1840-1900 (Garden City, New York: Doubleday & Co., 1956.), circa 1956 (Box 2, Folder 75)
- Photographs, circa 1885-circa 1930; Series III; 3
  Photographs collected by De Quille and his family.
  - J. B. Blanchard & Co., Portrait of Dan De Quille, circa 1885 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    James Brainard Blanchard (1837-1903) owned and operated the J. B. Blanchard & Co. in Los Angeles, California, circa 1880-1902.
  - Werts, Perry D., Portrait of Dan De Quille, circa 1885 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    Perry D. Werts (1857-1916) was a photographer in Iowa City, Iowa.
  - Gravesite of De Quille in Oak Ridge Cemetery, West Liberty, Iowa, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 78)
- Other Papers, 1875-circa 1898; Series IV; 16
  Series IV is organized into two subseries: Ephemera and Newspaper Clippings.
  - Ephemera
    Arranged chronologically
    Ephemera collected and created by De Quille.
    - Ticket to a clam-bake at Katama in Edgartown, Massachusetts, 1875 August 22 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Scrapbook sheets, circa 1891 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 91)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    Arranged alphabetically by topic followed by oversize clippings.
    Newspaper clippings collected by De Quille and his heirs. The bulk of the clippings document topics related to Alaska, economics, and scientific subjects, with smaller quantities of clippings about other topics.
  - Alaska, circa 1880-1895 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Economics, circa 1880-1895 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - History, circa 1880-1895 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Humor, circa 1880-1895 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - International, circa 1880-1895 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Mining, circa 1880-1895 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - National expansion, circa 1880-1895 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Nevada, circa 1880-1895 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Obituaries of De Quille, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Scientific subjects, circa 1880-1895 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Social critiques, circa 1880-1895 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Oversize newspaper clippings
    - Alaska, circa 1880-1895 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 92)
    - Obituaries of De Quille, 1898 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 93)
    - Scientific subjects, circa 1880-1895 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 94)
    - Superstition, 1883-1888 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 95)